A Guide to the Roanoke Valley YWCA Archives1901-1969
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Roanoke Valley YWCA Archives 1901-1969
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 180
9.1 linear feet
Roanoke Valley YWCA
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to the Department by the Board of the YWCA on 20 April 1983
Biographical/Historical Information
The organization began in 1913 after meeting at the Roanoke home of Mrs. A. J. Kennard. The first permanent organization meeting was held in January of 1914 where it met at the Green Memorial Methodist Church. With 1,153 pledge memberships, the E.W. Tinsley property at 415 Roanoke Street was chosen as the first home of the Association. In 1923 the program was extended to African American girls and women with the formation of the Phyllis Wheatley Branch which by the 1950s was called the Lula Williams Memorial Branch. The organization's headquarters began meeting a structure built specifically for the ssociation at the corner of First Street and Franklin Road., S.W. The building was dedicated on May 28, 1928.
As of 2002, the organization was called the YWCA of the Roanoke Valley. Its Executive Director was Pat Reynolds. An indication as to the services and programs it offers can be found in the organization's stated mission which is to "empower women and eliminate racism, the YWCA provides programs in these core areas: residence, child care and youth development, community and leadership development, advocacy and public policy, racial and social justice, targeted special-needs programs, and health and fitness."
Scope and Content Information
The collection includes minutes, reports, newsletters, records of the organizations multiple activities, photographs and clippings. There are a few files involved in the WPA Writers Program.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Materials arranged in chronological order
Organization
The collection has been arranged in five series. Photographs and oversize materials will be removed to appropriate locations as staff permits. There is only a rough inventory of the collection.
Series I--Board of Directors (1918-1969); Series II--Fiscal Records (1925-1969); Series III--Executive Director's File (1901-1951); Series IV--Committees ( - ); Series V--Photographs and Clippings ( - ).
Contents List
- Board of Directors 1918-1969
  - Minutes 1918 (Box-folder Folder 1.1)
  - Minutes 1922-1925 (Box-folder Folder 1.2)
  - Minutes 1926-1928 (Box-folder Folder 1.3)
  - Minutes 1928-1930 (Box-folder Folder 1.4)
  - Minutes 1930-1932 (Box-folder Folder 1.5)
  - Minutes 1932-1935 (Box-folder Folder 1.6)
  - Minutes 1935-1936 (Box-folder Folder 1.7)
  - Minutes 1937-1939 (Box-folder Folder 1.8)
  - Minutes 1937-1939 (Box-folder Folder 1.9)
  - Minutes 1940 (Box-folder Folder 1.10)
  - Minutes 1.11 (Box-folder Folder 1.11)
  - Minutes 1941 (Box-folder Folder 1.12)
  - Minutes 1942 (Box-folder Folder 1.13)
  - Minutes 1942-1943 (Box-folder Folder 1.14)
  - Minutes 1943 (Box-folder Folder 1.15)
  - Minutes 1944 (Box-folder Folder 1.16)
  - Minutes 1944 (Box-folder Folder 1.17)
  - Minutes 1945 (Box-folder Folder 1.18)
  - Minutes 1945 (Box-folder Folder 1.19)
  - Minutes 1946 (Box-folder Folder 1.20)
  - Minutes 1946 (Box-folder Folder 1.21)
  - Minutes 1947 (Box-folder Folder 2.1)
  - Minutes 1947 (Box-folder Folder 2.2)
  - Minutes 1948 (Box-folder Folder 2.3)
  - Minutes 1948 (Box-folder Folder 2.4)
  - Story of Roanoke YWCA 1949 (Box-folder Folder 2.5)
  - Minutes 1949 (Box-folder Folder 2.6)
  - Minutes 1949 (Box-folder Folder 2.7)
  - YWCA in Review 1950 (Box-folder Folder 2.8)
  - Minutes 1950 (Box-folder Folder 2.9)
  - Minutes 1950 (Box-folder Folder 2.10)
  - YWCA 1951 (Box-folder Folder 2.11)
  - Minutes 1951 (Box-folder Folder 2.12)
  - Minutes 1951 (Box-folder Folder 2.13)
  - YWCA 1952 (Box-folder Folder 2.14)
  - Minutes 1952 (Box-folder Folder 2.15)
  - Minutes 1952 (Box-folder Folder 2.16)
  - All Around the Year around YWCA 1954 (Box-folder Folder 2.17)
  - Minutes 1953 (Box-folder Folder 2.18)
  - Minutes 1954 (Box-folder Folder 2.19)
  - Minutes 1955 (Box-folder Folder 2.20)
  - Minutes 1955 (Box-folder Folder 2.21)
  - Minutes 1956 (Box-folder Folder 2.22)
  - Minutes 1956 (Box-folder Folder 2.23)
  - Minutes 1957 (Box-folder Folder 2.24)
  - Minutes 1957 (Box-folder Folder 2.25)
  - Minutes 1958 (Box-folder Folder 2.26)
  - Minutes 1958 (Box-folder Folder 2.27)
  - Minutes 1959 (Box-folder Folder 2.28)
  - Minutes 1960 (Box-folder Folder 2.29)
  - Minutes 1961 (Box-folder Folder 2.30)
  - Minutes 1962 (Box-folder Folder 2.31)
  - YWCA Annual Report 1969 (Box-folder Folder 2.32)
  - Board-President Correspondence (Box-folder Folder 2.33)
- Fiscal Records 1925-1969
  - Budget Manuals (Box-folder Folder 3.1)
  - Maintenance Finance Campaign 1935-1936 (Box-folder Folder 3.2)
  - Advancement Fund 1952 (Box-folder Folder 3.3)
  - Debt Retirement Fund 1939-1941 (Box-folder Folder 3.4)
  - Debt Retirement Fund 1956 (Box-folder Folder 3.5)
  - Centennial Fund 1955-1957 (Box-folder Folder 3.6)
  - Budget 1929 (Box-folder Folder 3.7)
  - Budget 1929 (Box-folder Folder 3.8)
  - Finance 1930 (Box-folder Folder 3.9)
  - Budget 1931 (Box-folder Folder 3.10)
  - Budget 1932 (Box-folder Folder 3.11)
  - Finance 1933 (Box-folder Folder 3.12)
  - Finance 1934 (Box-folder Folder 3.13)
  - Budget 1935 (Box-folder Folder 3.14)
  - Finance 1936 (Box-folder Folder 3.15)
  - Finance 1937-1940 (Box-folder Folder 3.16)
  - Finance Committee 1937 (Box-folder Folder 3.17)
  - Finance Committee 1938 (Box-folder Folder 3.18)
  - Budget 1938 (Box-folder Folder 3.19)
  - Finance Committee 1939 (Box-folder Folder 3.20)
  - Budget 1939 (Box-folder Folder 3.21)
  - Budget (Phyllis Wheatley Branch) 1939 (Box-folder Folder 3.22)
  - Budget 1940 (Box-folder Folder 3.23)
  - Budget (Phyllis Wheatley Branch) 1940 (Box-folder Folder 3.24)
  - Finance 1941 (Box-folder Folder 3.25)
  - Budget 1941 (Box-folder Folder 3.26)
  - Budget (Phyllis Wheatley Branch) 1941 (Box-folder Folder 3.27)
  - Finance 1942 (Box-folder Folder 3.28)
  - Budget (Phyllis Wheatley Branch) 1942 (Box-folder Folder 3.29)
  - Audit 1943 (Box-folder Folder 3.30)
  - Budget 1943 (Box-folder Folder 3.31)
  - Audit 1944 (Box-folder Folder 3.32)
  - Budget 1944 (Box-folder Folder 3.33)
  - Finances 1944 (Box-folder Folder 3.34)
  - Audit 1945 (Box-folder Folder 3.35)
  - Budget 1945 (Box-folder Folder 3.36)
  - Finance Committee 1945 (Box-folder Folder 3.37)
  - Finance 1945 (Box-folder Folder 3.38)
  - Audit 1946 (Box-folder Folder 3.39)
  - Finance Committee 1947 (Box-folder Folder 3.40)
  - Finance 1946 (Box-folder Folder 3.41)
  - Audit 1947 (Box-folder Folder 3.42)
  - Finance Committee 1947 (Box-folder Folder 3.43)
  - Finance 1947 (Box-folder Folder 3.44)
  - Finance Committee 1948 (Box-folder Folder 3.45)
  - Finance Committee 1949 (Box-folder Folder 3.46)
  - Finance Committee 1950 (Box-folder Folder 3.47)
  - Budget 1951 (Box-folder Folder 3.48)
  - Finance Statement 1951 (Box-folder Folder 3.49)
  - Finance Committee 1951 (Box-folder Folder 3.50)
  - Finance statement 1952 (Box-folder Folder 4.1)
  - Budget 1952 (Box-folder Folder 4.2)
  - Finance Committee 1952 (Box-folder Folder 4.3)
  - Budget 1953 (Box-folder Folder 4.4)
  - Finance Statement 1953 (Box-folder Folder 4.5)
  - Finance Committee 1953 (Box-folder Folder 4.6)
  - Audit 1954 (Box-folder Folder 4.7)
  - Budget 1954 (Box-folder Folder 4.8)
  - Finance Statement 1954 (Box-folder Folder 4.9)
  - Finance Committee 1954 (Box-folder Folder 4.10)
  - Audit 1955 (Box-folder Folder 4.11)
  - Budget 1955 (Box-folder Folder 4.12)
  - Finance Statement 1955 (Box-folder Folder 4.13)
  - Finance Committee 1955 (Box-folder Folder 4.14)
  - Audit 1956 (Box-folder Folder 4.15)
  - Budget 1956 (Box-folder Folder 4.16)
  - Finance Statement 1956 (Box-folder Folder 4.17)
  - Finance Committee 1956 (Box-folder Folder 4.18)
  - Audit 1957 (Box-folder Folder 4.19)
  - Budget 1957 (Box-folder Folder 4.20)
  - Finance Statement 1957 (Box-folder Folder 4.21)
  - Finance Committee 1957 (Box-folder Folder 4.22)
  - Audit 1958 (Box-folder Folder 4.23)
  - Budget 1958 (Box-folder Folder 4.24)
  - Finance Committee 1958 (Box-folder Folder 4.25)
  - Finance Statement 1958 (Box-folder Folder 4.26)
  - Audit 1959 (Box-folder Folder 4.27)
  - Budget 1959 (Box-folder Folder 4.28)
  - Finance Statement 1959 (Box-folder Folder 4.29)
  - Finance Committee 1959 (Box-folder Folder 4.30)
  - Audit 1960 (Box-folder Folder 4.31)
  - Budget 1960 (Box-folder Folder 4.32)
  - Finance Statement 1960 (Box-folder Folder 4.33)
  - Finance Committee 1960 (Box-folder Folder 4.34)
  - Audit 1961 (Box-folder Folder 5.1)
  - Finance Statement 1961 (Box-folder Folder 5.2)
  - Finance Committee 1961 (Box-folder Folder 5.3)
  - Audit 1962 (Box-folder Folder 5.4)
  - Budget 1962 (Box-folder Folder 5.5)
  - Finance Statement 1962 (Box-folder Folder 5.6)
  - Finance Committee 1962 (Box-folder Folder 5.7)
  - Audit 1963 (Box-folder Folder 5.8)
  - Budget 1963 (Box-folder Folder 5.9)
  - Finance Committee 1963 (Box-folder Folder 5.10)
  - Finance Statement 1963 (Box-folder Folder 5.11)
  - Audit 1964 (Box-folder Folder 5.12)
  - Budget 1964 (Box-folder Folder 5.13)
  - Finance 1964 (Box-folder Folder 5.14)
  - Finance Committee 1964 (Box-folder Folder 5.15)
  - Audit 1965 (Box-folder Folder 5.16)
  - Finance Statement 1965 (Box-folder Folder 5.17)
  - Finance Committee 1965 (Box-folder Folder 5.18)
  - Audit 1966 (Box-folder Folder 5.19)
  - Audit 1967 (Box-folder Folder 5.20)
  - Finance 1968 (Box-folder Folder 5.21)
  - Finance 1969 (Box-folder Folder 5.22)
- Executive Director's File 1901-1951
  - History (Box-folder Folder 6.1)
  - Constitution and By Laws (Box-folder Folder 6.2)
  - Brochures and activity promotions (Box-folder Folder 6.3)
  - National Board 1940-1943 (Box-folder Folder 6.4)
  - Protective agencies of Records 1940 (Box-folder Folder 6.5)
  - Schools of Roanoke 1940 (Box-folder Folder 6.6)
  - Fletcher Farm Seminar on Religion 1935 (Box-folder Folder 6.7)
  - General Correspondence-National Board 1935 (Box-folder Folder 6.8)
  - General Correspondence 1935 (Box-folder Folder 6.9)
  - Industrial Department (Box-folder Folder 6.10)
  - Institutes for Southern Social Work Executives 1934 (Box-folder Folder 6.11)
  - Movie 1941 (Box-folder Folder 6.12)
  - National Convention 1940 (Box-folder Folder 6.13)
  - Newsletter (Box-folder Folder 6.14)
  - Program Planning (Box-folder Folder 6.15)
  - Southern Summer School for Women Workers in Industry 1935 (Box-folder Folder 6.16)
  - Staff (Box-folder Folder 6.17)
  - Staff--National Association of Employed Officers of YWCA (Box-folder Folder 6.18)
  - Staff--National Association of Employed Officers of YWCA Union Proposal 1936 (Box-folder Folder 6.19)
  - Bulletin on Union Proposal 1936-1937 (Box-folder Folder 6.20)
  - Bulletin Material 1931-1937 (Box-folder Folder 6.21)
  - National Association of Employed Officers Standards 1940 (Box-folder Folder 6.22)
  - National Association of Employed Officers and Social Change 1901-1940 (Box-folder Folder 6.23)
  - General Secretary's News 1940 (Box-folder Folder 6.24)
  - Report of Professional Relations Committee 1938-1940 (Box-folder Folder 6.25)
  - Report of Finance Chairman 1938-1940 (Box-folder Folder 6.26)
  - Staff Training (Box-folder Folder 6.27)
- Committees
  - Adult Activities 1965-1975 (Box-folder Folder 7.1)
  - Branch (Box-folder Folder 7.2)
  - Phyllis Wheatley Branch (Box-folder Folder 7.3)
  - Building (Box-folder Folder 7.4)
  - Building Inventory 1938 (Box-folder Folder 7.5)
  - Building Inventory 1938 (Box-folder Folder 7.6)
  - Camp (Box-folder Folder 7.7)
  - Camp Kwanianna (Box-folder Folder 7.8)
  - Camp Tree Top (Box-folder Folder 7.9)
  - Clubs (Box-folder Folder 7.10)
  - Club R.I.F. (Box-folder Folder 7.11)
  - Club Second Cup of Coffee (Box-folder Folder 7.12)
  - Club Second Cup of Coffee Minutes 1951-1955 (Box-folder Folder 7.13)
  - Young Adult Council (Box-folder Folder 7.14)
  - Girl Reserves 1939-1943 (Box-folder Folder 7.15)
  - Girl Reserves (Box-folder Folder 7.16)
  - Girl Reserves (Box-folder Folder 7.17)
  - Health Education (Box-folder Folder 7.18)
  - Industrial and Business Girls (Box-folder Folder 7.19)
  - Membership Committee (Box-folder Folder 7.20)
  - Race Relations (Box-folder Folder 7.21)
  - Residence (Box-folder Folder 7.22)
  - Residence (Box-folder Folder 7.23)
  - Solo Parents Club (Box-folder Folder 7.24)
  - Committee World Fellowship (Box-folder Folder 7.25)
- Photographs and Clippings
  - 13 photographs YWCA (Box Box 8)
  - Negatives (Box Box 8)
  - Programs/Clippings 1965-1966 (Box Box 8)
  - Local News (Box Box 8)
- Scrapbooks
  - YWCA Building Accounts 1926 (Box Box 1)
  - YWCA Ledger 1940's (Box Box 2)
  - YWCA, Building Maintenance Ledger, n.d. Accounts, Expenses Receipts 1916-1925 (Box Box 3)